    <section id="intro_imap_and_cyrus">
        <title>Introduction to IMAP <emphasis>(FIXME: OLD)</emphasis></title>

        <section>
            <title>What is IMAP and Why Should I Use It?</title>

            <para>This definition is from the <ulink
            url="http://www.computeruser.com/resources/dictionary/dictionary.html">
            <citetitle>ComputerUser.com High-Tech
            Dictionary</citetitle></ulink>:</para>

            <para><emphasis>I</emphasis>nternet
            <emphasis>M</emphasis>essage <emphasis>A</emphasis>ccess
            <emphasis>P</emphasis>rotocol. A protocol that allows a user to
            perform certain electronic mail functions on a remote server
            rather than on a local computer. Through IMAP the user can
            create, delete, or rename mailboxes; get new messages; delete
            messages; and perform search functions on mail. A separate
            protocol is required for sending mail. Also called Internet
            Mail Access Protocol.</para>


            <section>
                <title>IMAP vs. POP</title>

                <para>IMAP allows the user to read email from many different
                locations and accounts because email folders are stored on the
                server, locally, at the home or the office, for instance. Even
                saved and read messages are stored on the IMAP server. POP
                only stores new unread messages on the server, and the read and
                saved messages are stored locally. To force POP to not delete
                email once it has been read can create many copies of the
                same email, creating a waste of space and confusion. However,
                IMAP is usually more complicated to set up. If you only have
                one email account, POP is most likely your best choice. If you
                want to access more than one account, from different locations,
                IMAP will probably serve you most efficiently. </para>

            </section>
            <!-- Not too sure about having these here
            <section>
                <title>Cyrus vs Maildir</title>
                <para></para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>Cyrus vs mbox</title>
                <para></para>
            </section> -->
        </section>


        <section>

            <title>What is Cyrus IMAP and Why Should I Use It?</title>

            <section>
                <title>Cyrus Features</title>

                <para>Cyrus IMAP provides a robust, scalable mail
                architecture.  It provides client access through IMAP
                and POP3, the two most common mail presentation protocols
                defined by open standards.  Through the use of the SASL
                authentication, it supports a variety of authentication
                mechanisms and back-ends.  It supports wrapping IMAP and
                POP3 in SSL and negotiating TLS in-channel.  It supports
                multiple storage pools for mailboxes, so adding mailbox
                space is relatively straight-forward.</para>

                <section>
                    <title>Cyrus IMAP vs. Washington IMAP <emphasis>(FIXME: OLD)</emphasis></title>

                    <para>Cyrus has its own mailbox database which is standalone
                    and increases performance, whereas Washington uses the stanard
                    UNIX mailbox format, which was designed for a smaller set of
                    users. Washington is portable to more UNIX and non-UNIX systems
                    than Cyrus. The main difference is that with Cyrus, you don't
                    have to add new users to your linux box (i.e. in /etc/passwd)
                    to add new mail users, and with Washington, you do.</para>
                </section>

                <section>
                    <title>Cyrus vs. Courier</title>
                    <para></para>
                </section>

                <section>
                    <title>Cyrus vs. Other IMAP Servers</title>
                    <para></para>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>

    </section>
<!-- vim:ft=docbkxml
-->
