<section id="maintenance">
    <title>Maintenance</title>
    <section>
        <title>Managing Mailboxes with <command>cyradm</command></title>

        <section>
            <title>Running <command>cyradm</command></title>

            <para>The <command>cyradm</command> command is the main tool that
            Cyrus administrators use.  It allows an administrator to create,
            delete and rename mailboxes and manage quotas and ACLs.</para>

            <para>Assuming that your system is configured, running
            <command>cyradm</command> should simply be a matter of typing
            the command, although it is often located in an out-of-the-PATH
            directory, so you might need the full path.  Inevitably, a
            person will have problems authenticating the first time because
            he has neglected to limit the advertised SASL mechanisms and
            <command>cyradm</command> chooses a stronger mechanism than
            he has support for.  If you are unable to login, specify the
            --auth option with "login".  You might also not be working
            as cyrus, so the "--user cyrus" option may also be necessary.
            Of course, the IMAP server itself must'nt be forgotten, even
            if it is only "localhost".  So that simple command of starting
            <command>cyradm</command> ends up being something like this:

            <screen>
$ cyradm --user cyrus --auth login localhost
</screen>
            
            </para>

            <para>Upon successfully launching <command>cyradm</command>,
            you will be presented with a prompt inviting you to start mucking
            about with things.  A good place to start is, of course, "help."

            <screen>
$ cyradm --user cyrus --auth login localhost
IMAP Password:localhost.localdomain> help
authenticate, login, auth         authenticate to server
chdir, cd                         change current directory
createmailbox, create, cm         create mailbox
deleteaclmailbox, deleteacl, dam  remove ACLs from mailbox
deletemailbox, delete, dm         delete mailbox
disconnect, disc                  disconnect from current server
exit, quit                        exit cyradm
help, ?                           show commands
info                              display mailbox/server metadata
listacl, lam, listaclmailbox      list ACLs on mailbox
listmailbox, lm                   list mailboxes
listquota, lq                     list quotas on specified root
listquotaroot, lqr, lqm           show quota roots and quotas for mailbox
mboxcfg, mboxconfig               configure mailbox
reconstruct                       reconstruct mailbox (if supported)
renamemailbox, rename, renm       rename (and optionally relocate) mailbox
server, servername, connect       show current server or connect to server
setaclmailbox, sam, setacl        set ACLs on mailbox
setinfo                           set server metadata
setquota, sq                      set quota on mailbox or resource
version, ver                      display version info of current server
xfermailbox, xfer                 transfer (relocate) a mailbox to a different server
</screen>
            </para>

            <para>You may, of course, use any SASL mechanism you have
            configured instead of "login", but login tends to work more readily
            than more sophisticated mechanisms.  <command>cyradm</command>
            need not be run on localhost either.  The administration protocol
            is integrated in the IMAP protocol itself, so the tool has a
            level of network transparency.  It does not, however, support
            SSL/TLS, which is why using it on localhost is a good idead.</para>

            <para>The command shell will pass any command it does not recognize
            to your regular shell, which may be confusing at first.</para>

            <para>Resist the temptation to give administrative rights
            to accounts other than dedicated accounts--logging in with
            administrative rights with a regular mail client may cause
            unpredictable results.  It is not out of sheer laziness that
            all of my examples use "cyrus" as the admin user.</para>

            

        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Listing Mailboxes and Wildcards</title>

            <para>Listing users is done with the 'listmailbox' command,
                usually run as 'lm'.  There are not a lot of options with
                'lm', except in the wildcards that may be used.  As with
                shell wildcards, '*' matches anything; '%', on the other
                hand, matches anything <emphasis>except</emphasis> the
                hierarchy separator.  This allows only listing the top-level
                set of folders.  For example, let's list all of the folders:
                <screen>
localhost.localdomain> lm
news.announce (\HasNoChildren)  user.foo.bar (\HasNoChildren)   
user.foo (\HasChildren)         user.wcooley (\HasNoChildren)   
</screen>
                
                Now let's list only users' folders:<screen>
localhost.localdomain> lm user.*
user.foo (\HasChildren)        user.wcooley (\HasNoChildren)  
user.foo.bar (\HasNoChildren)  
</screen>

                Now, let's list only the top-level user folders:<screen>
localhost.localdomain> lm user.%
user.foo (\HasChildren)        user.wcooley (\HasNoChildren)  
</screen>
            
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Creating Mailboxes</title>

            <para>In order for a user to receive e-mail with Cyrus, his
                mailbox must first be created.  This is unlike many IMAP
                servers, where the user's INBOX is created initially upon
                delivery.  Because Cyrus does not rely on UNIX accounts
                to authenticate users nor does it operate with any user's
                privileges, it cannot know whether a mailbox is valid.</para>

            <para>There are patches which allow automatic creation of a
                user's INBOX (and pre-defined subfolders) upon login.
                Provided that your users will login before the expect to
                receive e-mail and that all available accounts should have
                mailboxes, this is a good method of removing some
                administrative burden.</para>

            <para>Creating a mailbox manually is simply a matter of using
                the 'createmailbox' command, usually abbreviated 'cm', and
                providing the correct namespace.  For users, that namespace
                is 'user.', so a mailbox for user 'wcooley' will be created
                as 'user.wcooley'.

                <screen>
localhost.localdomain> cm user.wcooley
localhost.localdomain> lm user.wcooley
user.wcooley (\HasNoChildren)  
</screen>
            </para>

        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Deleting a Mailbox</title>

            <para>To delete a mailbox, you must fix give the admin user
                'create' permissions on the mailbox.  To the surprise of
                many, the admin does not have this permission by default.
                Then you can delete the mailbox with 'dm'.

                <screen>
localhost> lam user.test
test lrswipcda
localhost.localdomain> dm user.test
deletemailbox: Permission denied
localhost> sam user.test cyrus c 
localhost> lam user.test
test lrswipcda
cyrus c
localhost> dm user.test
</screen>
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Managing Quotas</title>
            <para></para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Managing Access Control Lists</title>
            <para></para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Backups</title>
            <para></para>
    </section>
</section>
<!-- vim:ft=docbkxml
-->
